Guide to the Alva Rogers Papers MSS.407
Fales Library and Special Collections
Alva Rogers Papers
1964-2018
1986-2011
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rogers, Alva
MSS.407
11.5 Linear Feet in 12 manuscript boxes, 3 flat boxes, 3 card boxes, two CD boxes, one LP box, and one custom box.
12.1 Gigabytes in 348 computer files.
26 videocassettes
43 audiocassettes
6 sound tape reels
1 sound discs (vinyl)
Alva Rogers (born 1959) is an artist, playwright, vocalist, actress, and songwriter. Best known for her role as Eula Peazant in the 1991 film Daughters of the Dust, Rogers has been involved in numerous creative endeavors throughout her career. As a playwright, Rogers wrote plays such as Nightbathing, the doll plays, and Scooping the Darkness Empty. Rogers was also a vocalist in the New York City alternative rock group Band of Susans. This collection contains materials pertaining to her artistic work such as scripts, sheet music, show programs, and recordings, as well as personal material including journals, letters, and photographs. Audiovisual and born-digital materials including recorded live performances are also included in this collection. This collection spans from 1964 to 2018 with the bulk of the material dating between 1986-2011.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Scope and Contents
The Alva Rogers Papers contain material related to Rogers's life and her creative works as a playwright, songwriter, actress, vocalist, and visual artist. The collection is mostly comprised of various ephemera relating to Rogers's theatrical performances and art shows as well as scripts and sheet music written or performed by Rogers. The collection documents Rogers's creative processes with notated manuscripts, research, and source materials. Included in the collection are scripts for her work of magical realism the doll plays, script and score for her musical Sunday: a Musical Fable, and a full length audio recording of a 1995 performance of Nightbathing. Also included are personal materials such as journals, letters, and photo albums, mostly relating to her life in New York City. The collection also documents her life as a professional artist and scholar with materials such as fellowship applications, awards, contracts, scholarship letters, and a copy of Rogers's Master in Fine Arts thesis from Brown University.
Biographical / Historical
Alva Rogers is an artist, playwright, vocalist, songwriter, and actress for theatre and films. Rogers was born on October 22, 1959 in New York City, where she was raised by her father. Rogers attended The High School of Music & Art in Manhattan, where she graduated with a concentration in vocal music. Rogers began her academic career with the intention of writing about race relations, gender, and the politics of African American music as a journalist, and received a Bachelor's degree in American History from Marietta College. She also lived in Europe for a short time after graduation. Rogers went on to receive a Master of Fine Arts in Musical Theater Writing from Tisch School of the Arts at New York University in 1995, a Master of Fine Arts in Literary Arts from Brown University in 1998, and a Master of Arts in Teaching with a focus on History from Bard College in 2013. Rogers has one daughter, India Rogers-Shepp.
Rogers became active in the downtown performance scene in 1988. She began her vocal career with Butch Morris as a member of his various vocal ensembles. She performed as a vocalist with Vernonn Reid, Elliot Sharp, Wayne Horvitz and Band of Susans. Rogers regularly performed her original compositions and arrangements at the Knitting Factory, a performance venue on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. She appeared on "Live at the Knitting Factory", a compilation album released by A&M Records in 1989. She also performed with Urban Bush Women, Laurie Carlos, Kaylynn Sullivan and the Rodeo Caldonia High Fidelity Performance Theatre.
Rogers's work, informed by her experiences with racism, sexism, the Black Power movement, and feminism, draws on themes of dreams, magical realism, and surrealism - exploring ideas of emotion and memory. Her work often includes multimedia elements such as music and puppetry. Rogers has been highly awarded for her work as a writer and performer, including receiving a New York Foundation for the Arts Fellowship in Performance in 1988, a Franklin Furnace Fund for Performance Art Grant for the development of the bride who became frightened when she saw life open in 1994, a Bessie Award as co-creator of the radio play Stained in 1995, a Rockefeller Multi-Arts Production Grant to produce the doll plays in 2001, a Jim Henson Foundation Grant to develop and produce the musicals Mermaid and Sunday: A Musical Fable at The Women's Project in 2003, and a New York Foundation of the Arts Grant in Playwriting in 2004. She was a resident at The Joseph Papp Public Theater from 2003 to 2005 and at the Hedgebrook Women's Writers colony in conjunction with Seattle Repertory Theater in 2011.
As a film actress, Rogers appeared in Spike Lee's 1988 film School Daze in the role of Doris Witherspoon, and made appearances in various other films by Lee. Her work in School Daze attracted the attention of Julie Dash, director of Daughters of the Dust (1991). She was also featured in Kerry James Marshall's film The Doppler Incident (1997). Rogers also collaborated on various film projects with writer and director Lisa Jones.
As of 2020 Rogers continues to live and work in New York City.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donation of Alva Rogers, 2014; an additional accession was donated by Rogers in 2019. The accession number associated with these gifts are 2014.407 and 2019.059.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Series I. Artistic Works; Series II: Biographical Materials; Series III. Administrative Files.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Dramatists, American.; Women dramatists; Playwriting.; Women artists.; African American artists -- 21st century; African American artists -- 20th century; African American theater; African American women.; African American women singers.; African American actresses; African American women performance artists; Rogers, Alva
- Series I. Artistic Works, 1986-2011; 7.5 Linear Feet in six manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, 2 card boxes, one LP box, and one custom 12" box.; 4 sound cassettes (dat); 23 audiocassettes; 16 videocassettes (s-vhs); 1 sound discs (vinyl); 4 sound tape reels; 11.65 Gigabytes in 15 recordings.
  Scope and Contents
  This series represents Rogers's creative works as a playwright, songwriter, actress, vocalist, and visual artist. The paper materials contain programs, flyers, and news clippings/reviews for Rogers's theatrical performances and art shows as well as scripts and sheet music for works written or performed by Rogers. The born-digital, and audiovisual materials primarily include recordings of performances by Rogers as well as interviews she conducted while conceptualizing the bride who became frightened when she say life open. Most material in this series is grouped by the title of the work, although some is grouped by subject or performance venue. Included in this series are the script and score for her musical Sunday: a Musical Fable and a full length audio recording of a 1995 performance of Nightbathing.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by work title, subject, or performance venue.
  - Acting, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - All the Marys Weep (Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0077)
  - ALVA, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2-7, Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0053)
  - Alva Rogers Quartet, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Alva Rogers V.O. Reel, undated (Box 13, Video 407.0015)
  - Atlas: An Opera in Three Parts, undated (Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0040)
  - Band of Susans, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 11, Folder 1, Box 19, Disc 407.0085)
  - belly: three shorts, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Black Cameo Project, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - blind girl, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12, Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0061)
  - the bride who became frightened when she saw life open, 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 13-14, Box 13, Video 407.0017, 407.0024, 407.0025, Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0032, 407.0037, 407.0038, 407.0039, 407.0044)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music Next Wave Festival: Artists in Action, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Butch Morris Octet, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cage Revisited, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Cake, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Carmella and King Kong, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Central Page Summer Stage--Press, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Daughters of the Dust, 1989-2011 (Box 1, Folder 19-23, Box 11, Folder 4, Box Shared Fales 020, Folder 15, Box 12, Video 407.0001)
  - Dear India--poems, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - the doll plays, 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 25-28, Box 2, Folder 1-5, Box 11, Folder 5, Box Shared Fales 020, Folder 16, Box 12, Video 407.0006, Box 13, Video 407.0019)
  - Doppler Incident, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - eggwhites, undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - glow (in my house), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - How'd You Get Your Teeth So White?, 1987-1991; undated (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0060, Box 18, Reel 407.0084, 407.0086, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_1, Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0045)
  - Intersection for the Arts and Festival 2000, October, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - imusicircus, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jam session with Butch Morris and Arlene Schloss, 1986 (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0091)
  - Kissing and Telling, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11-12, Box 12, Video 407.0008, 407.0011, Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0078)
  - Knitting Factory Performances, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13-14, Box 12, Video 407.0002, Box 13, Video 407.0026, Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0030, 407.0034, Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0074, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_3)
  - Late Nite Series, 2006 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_14)
  - The Mary Trilogy, undated (Box 12, Video 407.0003)
  - Maya in the Cities--Hedgebrook Women Playwrights Festival, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miss Mermaid's Coral Cove, 1996; undated (Box 13, Video 407.0023, Box 17, Item 1, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_13)
  - Moving into the Dead of Night, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Musical Theater Rehearsals, 2002 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_4)
  - National Puppetry Festival, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Negro Doll Factory Music, 1989-1990 (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0065)
  - New American Radio, 1989-1991 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_5)
  - Nightbathing, 1995-2001; undated (Box 2, Folder 17-18, Box 3, Folder 1-7, Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0041, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_6)
  - Nightbathing--Complete Show, May 4, 1995; cuid6285 (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0057, Box Electronic Records, Item mss.407.cuid6285)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 90 min.
    A recorded reading of the musical: Nightbathing, performed by Alva Rogers at The Public Theatre in New York City.
    Track listing:
    1. Prologue 2. A Beautiful Beginning 3. Hallie Harper is Dead 4. The Question 5. Where's Hallie? 6. Girlfriends 7. M.L.King is Dead 8. The Only Woman 9. We'll take care of you (Song: Come Home) 10. Poison Milk 11. Nightbathing 12. Call me Sister 13. Stained
  - O'Neil Puppetry Conference, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Organdy Falsetto, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - P.S. 122: Field Trips, Benefits, and Decade Show, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 10, Box 12, Video 407.0004, 407.0018, Box 13, Video 407.0014, 407.0020, 407.0021, 407.0022, Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0052)
  - Performances at The Kitchen, 1991 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_2, Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0075)
  - Pizza Party--Live at the Knitting Factory, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Press, 1986-1999 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Press Releases, 1988-2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ready for Love, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Reno Roast (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Roulette, 1986 (Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0029, 407.0042)
  - School Daze, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - scooping the darkness empty, 2006; undated (Box 4, Folder 2-4, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_9)
  - Sesame Street, 1993; undated (Box 13, Video 407.0016, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_15)
  - Songs from the Travelogue, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Songs, undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_10)
  - Spoleto Project, 1991 (Box 18, Reel 407.0087-407.0089)
  - Sunday: A Musical Fable, 1994-2002; undated (Box 4, Folder 6-9, Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0031, 407.0043, Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0050, Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0073, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_8)
  - Wall to Wall Music Festival--Performing Garage, 1984 (Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0028)
  - Water in the Desert, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - We Could be Sheroes, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - what remnants remain, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - the whole wide world, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 13, Box 12, Video 407.0010)
  - Woman Without Adornment, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series II. Biographical Materials, 1964-2018; 5.25 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, one flat box, and 2 card boxes.; 5 audiocassette; 1 Gigabytes in 2 recordings; 67 Megabytes in 21 files.
  This series contains Rogers's personal materials including journals, school records, correspondence, child's drawings, and personal photo albums and scrapbooks. Correspondences are between Rogers and her friends, family, and professional connections and include letters, birthday cards, and postcards.
  This series was not arranged.
  - Alva Rodgers Bio, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Elementary School Records, 1964-1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Blanche Elaine "Andy" Rogers Funeral Program, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - F. Joseph Rogers Funeral Program, 2018 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - How I Learned to Drive--Script signed by Paula Vogel, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1983-2018 (Box 5, Folder 6-50, Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Diaries and Journals, 1989-2008 (Box 6, Folder 5-7, Box 7, Folder 1-7)
  - Scrapbooks, Photographs, and Slides, undated (Box 7, Folder 8-9, Box 8, Folder 1-9, Box 11, Folder 7, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_11)
  - The High School of Music and Art Yearbook, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Rogers 58th Birthday, May 4, 1990 (Box 14, Audiocassette 407.0035, Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0059)
  - Semesters, undated (Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0027, 407.0066)
  - Chrispy Soloperto/Darnell Martin, 1992 (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0063)
  - India Sings, 2002 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_7)
- Series III. Administrative Files, 1986-2017; 3.25 Linear Feet In one manuscript box, one flat box, and two card boxes.; 3 audiocassettes; 1 sound cassettes (dat); 922 kilobytes in 310 computer files.
  This series contains various administrative files including copyright documents, contracts and letters of agreement, awards, and applications. Also included are demo tapes, recorded voice lessons, and the files used to build Rogers's website.
  - Theatre Communications Group Residency, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Membership Cards, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Museum Exhibition: "Black Radical Women 1965-85", 2017 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Grants, 2004-2006 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - School Daze Contract, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Letters of Agreement and Contracts, 1990-2011 (Box 9, Folder 7, 18)
  - Letters of Inquiry, 1990-1998 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Teaching on the Hill, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Brown University Awards and Honors, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - New York University Awards, Honors, and Transcripts, 1993-1995 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Acceptance Letters (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
  - Jerome Fellowship, 2016 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Alva Rogers Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Submissions and Applications, 1996-2007 (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
  - Copyright Certificates, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 19-20)
  - Awards, 1995-1998 (Box 9, Folder 21, Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Articles written by Alva Rogers, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Speech at Trinity College, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Tisch School of the Arts Thesis, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Master of Fine Arts Thesis, Brown University, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 26-28)
  - Demo Tapes, undated (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0046, Box 16, Audiocassette 407.0079)
  - Voice Lesson, undated (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0047)
  - Regional and International Accents, undated (Box 15, Audiocassette 407.0068)
  - Files used for Website, undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_407_ER_12)